Vincent Ferrini Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Vincent Ferrini Papers.
n.d., 1949-1977.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Center.
Ferrini, Vincent.
2.25 linear feet.
Vincent Ferrini was born 24 June 1913 in Saugus, Massachusetts, the son of Italian immigrants. Ferrini's first book of poems, No Smoke (1941), was written while he was employed by General Electric at the Lynn (MA) plant. In the early 1950s he edited a small magazine entitled Four Winds
MSS19970107
Biography
Vincent Ferrini was born 24 June 1913 in Saugus, Massachusetts, the son of Italian immigrants. He received his formal education in local schools and continued his learning through a self-initiated program of study. Ferrini's first book of poems, No Smoke (1941), was written while he was employed by General Electric at the Lynn (MA) plant. Much of his poetry focuses on social issues relating to his factory experiences with GE and other large companies. In the early 1950s he edited a small magazine entitled Four Winds.
Mr. Ferrini was married first to Margaret Duffy and then to artist Mary Shore. He is the father of a son and two daughters (one deceased). Presently residing in Gloucester, MA, he continues his literary activities. He also operates his own framemaking business.
For many years, Ferrini was a close friend of the poet Charles Olson (1910-1970), and has numerous acquaintances in literary circles.
Vincent Ferrini died on 24 December 2007 at the age of 94.
Scope and Content
The collection includes correspondence, manuscripts, notes, newspaper clippings, photographs and literary ephemera (posters, broadsides, and pamphlets).
Arrangement
Series I: Correspondence ( 1949-1973 ) includes correspondence to and from Vincent Ferrini and numerous friends and literary figures including Robin Blaser, Stan Brakhage, Cid Corman, Robert Creeley, Larry Eigner, Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Gerard Malanga, Charles Olson, and Kenneth Rexroth.
Series II: Manuscripts ( n.d., 1951-1970 ) contains Ferrini manuscripts as well as those of others.
Series III: Clippings and Ephemera ( n.d., 1977 ) include items that do not fall within Series I and II. Some materials can be identified and have been foldered individually.
Series IV: Photographs and AV Materials ( n.d., 1966 ) include items that do not fall within Series I and II. The collection includes two unidentified photographs and three audio tapes.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of literary materials, especially materials associated with Black Mountain College and the Beat Generation. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
Creeley, Robert. Words. New York: Charles Scribner's Sons, 1967. Inscribed “for Vincent in the pleasure of his place—with love, Bob Gloucester, Mass. July 27, 1967”Dodd Call No. B 5488
Ferrini, Vincent. Hermit of the Clouds. The Autobiography of Vincent Ferrini. [Japanese edition] Dodd Call No. A 4457b
Dorn, Edward. What I see in the Maximus Poems. N.P.: A Migrant Pamphlet, 1960. Inscribed “for Vincent first to see how the wind lieth O” Dodd Call No. WPS 3448
Olson, Charles. A Bibliography on America for Ed Dorn. San Francisco: City Lights Books, 1964. Inscribed “Vincent Ferrini `Given' + how to my other `Carp?'—with my own hands—today with this Indice written at the same time: Blessings on me, Little Lamb What a Lion I am today! D.V. [see p. 10-11, Vince] Wednesday January 20th 1966” Dodd Call No. WPS 3450
Olson, Charles. Charles Olson Reading at Berkeley. Transcribed by Zoe Brown. San Francisco: City Lights Books, 1966. Inscribed “I hope legitmame (sic)! Especially for you Charles” Dodd Call No.
Olson, Charles. The Distances/Poems. New York: Grove Press, Inc., 1960. Inscribed “For Vincent with love from Charles” Dodd Call No. C 5402
Olson, Charles. O'Ryan 2 4 6 8 10. N.P., n.d. Inscribed “for Vince: `My stars! Why, bless my necktie!' Love, O Gloucester Jan 31 59” Dodd Call No. WPS 3449
Olson, Charles. Y ☀ X Drawings by Corrado Cagli, Poems by Charles Olson. Black Sun Press, 1948. Inscribed “The House of...(for) Vincent Ferrini Charles Olson January 20th 1966...3rd—+ firing factor of the Coordinates Y ☀ X is the K” Dodd Call No. D 1493
Bibliography
About the Author:
An incomplete bibliography of Ferrini's work can be found in folder 255 as part of his correspondence with Brown University.
A brief biography of Ferrini can be found in Italian-American Authors and Their Contribution to American Literature (Vanni, 1949, pp. 99-100).
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Corman, Cid--Correspondence.; Eigner, Larry, 1927- --Correspondence.; Malanga, Gerard--Correspondence.; Olson, Charles, 1910-1970-- Correspondence.; Katsura, San--Correspondence.; Shaw, Louis--Correspondence.; Four winds.; Poetry Editing.; American poetry--20th century.; American poetry--Massachusetts.; American poetry--Periodicals.; Periodicals--Publishing.; American drama--20th century.; Massachusetts--Cultural affairs--Literature.; Gloucester (Mass.--Cultural affairs--Literature.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Manuscripts.; Notebooks.; Publications.; Photographs.; Audio Tapes.
Occupations:
Poet.; Author.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was purchased from Mr. Ferrini by the University in August 1972.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Correspondence, n.d., 1949-1973
  - Academy of American Poets, 1968-1969 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Anastas, Peter, 1966-1971 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Art Digest (see Kramer, Hilton)
  - Asphodel Bookshop (see Lowell, Jim)
  - The Atlantic Monthly, 1970 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Baldelli, Giovanni, 1955 (Box 1:, Folder 4-5)
  - Bay State Banner, 1967 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Beacon Press, 1969-1970 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Benson, Joyce, 1971 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Black Sparrow Press, 1969 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Blaine, Nell, 1969 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - Blaser, Robin, 1970 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - Bodley House Literary Agency, Ltd., 1949 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
  - Borash, Sam, 1972 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
  - Brakhage, Stan, 1963 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
  - Broburg, Jeane, 1970 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
  - Brown University Library (see Stoddard, Roger)
  - Buell, Carol, 197? (Box 1:, Folder 16)
  - Butterick, George, 1967-1972 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
  - Calhoun, Douglas, 1970-1972 (Box 1:, Folder 18)
  - Campbell, Paul, 1958-1959 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - City Lights Bookshop (see Ferlinghetti, Lawrence)
  - Coach House Press, 1970 (Box 1:, Folder 20)
  - Cohn, Lowell R., 1966 (Box 1:, Folder 21)
  - Coletti-Perucca, U., 1956 (Box 1:, Folder 22)
  - Coleman, Victor (see Coach House Press)
  - Conrad, Carolyn, 1971 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
  - Corman, Cid, 1949-1970 (Box 1:, Folder 24-65)
  - Costley, Bill, 1976 (Box 1:, Folder 66)
  - Creative Arts Festival, Kent State University, 1970 (Box 1:, Folder 67)
  - Crehan, Hubert, 1959-1970? (Box 1:, Folder 68)
  - Creeley, Robert, 1950-1967 (Box 1:, Folder 69-77)
  - Davis, Peter (see The Atlantic Monthly)
  - Dickson, William S., 1969 (Box 1:, Folder 78)
  - Doubleday and Co., 1968 (Box 1:, Folder 79)
  - Eigner, Larry, 1955-1970 (Box 1:, Folder 80-110)
  - Element Magazine, 1959 (Box 1:, Folder 111)
  - Esty, Jane, 1958 (Box 1:, Folder 112)
  - Ferlinghetti, Lawrence, 1956-1957 (Box 1:, Folder 113-114)
  - Ferrini, Paul, 1970-1971 (Box 2:, Folder 115)
  - Ferrini, Sheila, 1970 (Box 2:, Folder 116)
  - Ferrini, Vincent, 1958-1973 (Box 2:, Folder 117-121)
  - Fortune Press, Ltd., 1970 (Box 2:, Folder 122)
  - Garland, Joseph E., 1968 (Box 2:, Folder 123)
  - Givovskaya, Darya N. (Dorothy), 1971 (Box 2:, Folder 124)
  - Glassner, John, 1957 (Box 2:, Folder 125)
  - Glover, Al, 1969 (Box 2:, Folder 126)
  - Gold, Mike, 1958 (Box 2:, Folder 127)
  - Goliard/Santa Fe, 1972 (Box 2:, Folder 128)
  - Gotham Book Mart and Gallery, Inc., 1970-1971 (Box 2:, Folder 129)
  - Granich, Mike, 1956 (Box 2:, Folder 130)
  - Gratwick, H. (Mrs. William), 1964 (Box 2:, Folder 131)
  - Guggenheim Foundation, 1970 (Box 2:, Folder 132)
  - Hammond, John H., Jr., 1959 (Box 2:, Folder 133)
  - Harmon, Catherine (see Bodley House)
  - Harvard College Library (see Broburg, Jeane)
  - Hecht, Mike, 1976 (Box 2:, Folder 134)
  - Kelly, Robert, 1964-1965 (Box 2:, Folder 135-136)
  - Kennedy, Edward M. (Senator), 1970 (Box 2:, Folder 137)
  - The Kerryman Ltd. (Dublin, Ireland), 1969 (Box 2:, Folder 138)
  - Harvey, Jon, 1957 (Box 2:, Folder 139)
  - Hoffman, Daniel, 1969 (Box 2:, Folder 140)
  - International Publishers, 1969 (Box 2:, Folder 141)
  - Jeannine, n.d. (Box 2:, Folder 142)
  - Katsura, San, 1956-1971 (Box 2:, Folder 143-144)
  - Keys, John, 1964-1971 (Box 2:, Folder 145-147)
  - Kramer, Hilton, 1954-1956 (Box 2:, Folder 148-150)
  - Kunitz, Stanley, 1969 (Box 2:, Folder 151)
  - Lansing, Gerrit, 1963-1964 (Box 2:, Folder 152-154)
  - Laughlin, James, 1970 (Box 2:, Folder 155)
  - Layton, Irving, 1954 (Box 2:, Folder 156)
  - Lenk, Marjorie, n.d. (Box 2:, Folder 157)
  - Lia, Constantine, 1968 (Box 2:, Folder 158)
  - Library of Congress, Copyright Office, 1969 (Box 2:, Folder 159)
  - Lindo, 1970-1971 (Box 2:, Folder 160)
  - Lowell, Jim, 1954-1958 (Box 2:, Folder 161)
  - Lowenfels, Walter, 1956-1972 (Box 2:, Folder 162-164)
  - Lyle, David, 1971 (Box 2:, Folder 165)
  - MacFarland, Arthur (Box 2:, Folder 166)
  - Magaloni, Ignacio, 1958 (Box 2:, Folder 167)
  - Malanga, Gerard, 1970-1971 (Box 2:, Folder 168-182)
  - Mangione, Jene, 1969 (Box 2:, Folder 183)
  - Mangravite, Peppino, 1956 (Box 2:, Folder 184)
  - Mao Tun, 1957 (Box 2:, Folder 185)
  - Marro, George, n.d. (Box 2:, Folder 186)
  - Martin, John (see Black Sparrow Press)
  - May, James Boyer, 1957-1972 (Box 2:, Folder 187-190)
  - McNaughton, Duncan, 1970 (Box 2:, Folder 191)
  - Millett, Martha, 1956-1958 (Box 2:, Folder 192)
  - Morrill, Donald, 1968-1972 (Box 2:, Folder 193)
  - Mutiny Press (see Esty, Jane)
  - National Book Committee, 1970 (Box 2:, Folder 194)
  - Nelson, Truman, n.d. (Box 2:, Folder 195)
  - The New York Quarterly, 1970 (Box 2:, Folder 196)
  - Nixon, Rice, 1955 (Box 2:, Folder 197)
  - North Shore Magazine, 1969 (Box 2:, Folder 198)
  - Norton, Janet S., 1969 (Box 2:, Folder 199)
  - Olson, Betty, n.d., 1964 (Box 3:, Folder 200)
  - Olson, Charles, 1960-1969 (Box 3:, Folder 201-228)
  - Olson, Peter, 1963 (Box 3:, Folder 229)
  - Parker, Harvey, 1956 (Box 3:, Folder 230)
  - Poems of the People (see Torgerson, Eric)
  - Phoenix, 1969? (Box 3:, Folder 231)
  - Pingree School (see Norton, Janet S.)
  - Poetry Society of America, 1969 (Box 3:, Folder 232)
  - Ramos, George, n.d. (Box 3:, Folder 233)
  - Randall de Mondragon, Margaret, 1963-1970 (Box 3:, Folder 234)
  - Reitano, Joe, 1970 (Box 3:, Folder 235)
  - Rexroth, Kenneth, 1957 (Box 3:, Folder 236)
  - “Rory”, n.d., 1971 (Box 3:, Folder 237)
  - Rubenstein, Richard, 1951 (Box 3:, Folder 238)
  - Russell, Peter, 1955-1958 (Box 3:, Folder 239-241)
  - Sanders, Ed, 1963-1964 (Box 3:, Folder 242-243)
  - Sankey, John, 1957-1972 (Box 3:, Folder 244)
  - Sarbo, Lorra (Mrs. Peter D.), 1970 (Box 3:, Folder 245)
  - Sawyer, Paul, 1970, 1976 (Box 3:, Folder 246-247)
  - Schales, William, 1970 (Box 3:, Folder 248)
  - Shaw, Louis, 1965-1971 (Box 3:, Folder 249)
  - Shore, Mary, 1972 (Box 3:, Folder 250)
  - Sonster, Ray, 1963 (Box 3:, Folder 251)
  - Sparrow Magazine, n.d. (Box 3:, Folder 252)
  - Spoken Arts, Inc., 1970 (Box 3:, Folder 253)
  - Stefanile, Frank, 1955 (Box 3:, Folder 254)
  - Stoddard, Roger E., 1963 (Box 3:, Folder 255)
  - Sumac Press, 1970 (Box 3:, Folder 256)
  - Swallow Press, Inc., 1970 (Box 3:, Folder 257)
  - Taggart, John, 1971 (Box 3:, Folder 258-259)
  - Takagi, Yasaka, 1955 (Box 3:, Folder 260)
  - Taylor, Tom, 1970 (Box 3:, Folder 261)
  - Temple Bar Bookshop, 1970 (Box 3:, Folder 262)
  - Tension, n.d. (Box 3:, Folder 263)
  - Torgerson, Eric, 1970-1971 (Box 3:, Folder 264)
  - Tuttle, Charles E., Co., Inc., 1970 (Box 3:, Folder 265)
  - Unidentified Single letters, 1952-1976 (Box 3:, Folder 266)
  - University of Pennsylvania (see Hoffman, Daniel)
  - Ventures in Sound, 1955 (Box 3:, Folder 267)
  - Ventures in Sound, 1955 (Box 3:, Folder 268)
  - Vermont Stoveside Press, n.d., 1968 (Box 3:, Folder 269)
  - Villiers Publications (see Sankey, John)
  - WBZ-TV4, 1969 (Box 3:, Folder 270)
  - Wesleyan University Press, 1969 (Box 3:, Folder 271)
  - WGBH, 1970-1971 (Box 3:, Folder 272)
  - Williams, Jonathan, 1954-1968 (Box 3:, Folder 273-281)
  - Zimmerman, Daniel, 1970 (Box 3:, Folder 282)
  - Zobin, Mark, n.d. (Box 3:, Folder 283)
- Series II: Manuscripts, n.d., 1951-1970
  - Alcalay, Leor, 1970 (Box 3:, Folder 284)
  - Clarke, Jack, 1965 (Box 3:, Folder 285)
  - Corman, Cid, 1951? (Box 3:, Folder 286)
  - David-Neel, Alexandra (Box 3:, Folder 287)
  - Dlugoszewski, Lucia, n.d. (Box 3:, Folder 288)
  - Eigner, Larry, 1970 (Box 3:, Folder 289)
  - Ferrini, Paul (?), n.d. (Box 3:, Folder 290)
  - Ferrini, Vincent (Box 4)
    - Autobiography, n.d. (Box 4:, Folder 291)
    - “Endless Journey” (Box 4:, Folder 292)
    - “An Interior Dynasty”, n.d. (Box 4:, Folder 293)
    - “Irradiations for a Sanctuary”, n.d. (Box 4:, Folder 294)
    - “Mindscapes” (Box 4:, Folder 295)
    - Notes, n.d. (Box 4:, Folder 296)
    - “The Temple”, n.d. (Box 4:, Folder 297)
    - “The Weed”, n.d. (Box 4:, Folder 298)
  - Katsura, San, 1967 (Box 4:, Folder 299-300)
  - Malanga, Gerard, 1970 (Box 4:, Folder 301)
  - Olson, Charles, n.d., 1968 (Box 4:, Folder 302)
  - Taylor, Tom, n.d. (Box 4:, Folder 303)
  - Torgerson, Eric (?), n.d. (Box 4:, Folder 304)
  - Unidentified author(s), n.d. (Box 4:, Folder 305-306)
  - Weaver, Mike, n.d. (Box 4:, Folder 307)
- Series III: Clippings and Ephemera n.d., 1977
  - Newspaper clippings, n.d. (Box 4:, Folder 308)
  - Boston Globe Calendar, 1977 (Box 4:, Folder 309)
  - Ephemera, n.d. (Box 4:, Folder 310)
- Series IV: Photographs and AV Materials n.d., 1966
  - Unidentified, n.d., 1966 (Box 4:, Folder 311)
  - 3 Reel to reel tapes (unlabeled), n.d. (Box 5)